<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style/default.xsl"?>

<section title="Adding Text" level="1">
  
  <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></sourcecode>
  
  <p>The above .lvn script shows &quot;Hello World&quot; in the main text box. LVN files automatically translate text lines to Lua text functions. These functions (<code>paragraph.start</code>, <code>paragraph.append</code> and <code>paragraph.end</code>) can be replaced by custom versions if you want to add special functionality (replacing $name in text lines with the player's name for example).</p>
  
  <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[Different paragraphs...
...are on different lines

#Empty lines are ignored

When using NVL mode...
@clearText()
...you must clear the screen manually]]></sourcecode>
  
  <p>In NVL mode, the text box is fullscreen and each text line starts a new paragraph. To clear the text shown (start a new page), use the <code>clearText()</code> function.</p>
  
  <p>In ADV mode, only one paragraph is shown at a time -- <code>clearText</code> is called automatically when starting a new paragraph.</p>

  <section title="Who's Talking" level="2">
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[William: ...
William: ... ...
Balthasar: Pew pew
William: Argh]]></sourcecode>
    <p>A visual novel's text can be written like a book, or - as in the above example - in the style of a (screen)play. In the second case, the speaker's name must be included somewhere. The script above is actually a valid .lvn script and it can be used without modification. However, you would have to retype the speaker's full name for every line spoken and the name will be displayed as text in the text box. There's a <code>say</code> function that can be used to change the speaker name and text style. The speaker name, if changed through the <code>say</code> function, shows up in a separate name box. The optional text style argument can be used to make a certain character speak in a different font.</p>
    
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[@say("William")
...
... ...
@say("Balthasar")
Pew pew
@say("William")
Argh
@say()]]></sourcecode>
    <p>The <code>say</code> function doesn't have to be repeated for each line. It only needs to be used when the speaker changes. To revert back to the default speaker (for narration perhaps?), use <code>say</code> without any arguments.</p>
    <p>This doesn't solve having to type the names over and over, but that's easily solved by writing a function:</p>
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[@@
function sayWi()
    say("William")
end
function sayBa()
    say("Balthasar")
end
@@]]></sourcecode>
    <p>Add this function to <code>main.lua</code> and you can use <code>sayWi()</code> instead of typing out <code>say(&quot;William&quot;)</code> every time. It's shorter, and more importantly, protects you from typos. Mistyping a function causes a script error allowing you to easily find and fix the typo.</p>
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[@sayWi()
...
... ...
@sayBa()
Pew pew
@sayWi()
Argh
@say()]]></sourcecode>

    <p>The <code>registerSpeaker</code> function provides an alternative notation for changing the active speaker. In addition, it generates a <code>say_XXX</code> function that changes the active speaker without changing back at the end of line.</p>
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[@registerSpeaker("wi", "William")
@registerSpeaker("ba", "Balthasar")
#Using the $ syntax
$wi ...
$wi ... ...
$ba Pew pew
$wi Argh

#Using the new say_XXX functions
@say_wi()
...
... ...
@say_ba()
Pew pew
@say_wi()
Argh]]></sourcecode>
  </section>

  <section title="Dynamic Text" level="2">
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[@local myVariable = "World"
Hello $myVariable
NoSpaces${myVariable}BetweenWords]]></sourcecode>

    <p>Words starting with a $ will be replaced by the value of the variable with the same name (<code>registerSpeaker</code> takes precedence in case of a conflict). If the value of the variable is a function, that function will be called to generate the value to insert. A value of <code>nil</code> inserts no text at all.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Text Box" level="2">
    <sourcecode lang="lua"><![CDATA[customTextBox(TextMode.ADV, {
  textBounds={10, 460, 780, 130},
  textBackground="gui/adv-text-bg",
  textBackgroundExtra={x=0, y=450},
  nameTextBounds={10, 430, 250, 30},
  nameTextBackground="gui/adv-name-bg",
  nameTextBackgroundExtra={x=0, y=425}
})]]></sourcecode>

    <p>The <code>customTextBox</code> is the easiest way to customize the text box. The first argument is the text mode to change the text box for (<code>TextMode.ADV</code> or <code>TextMode.NVL</code>), the second argument is a Lua table with optional arguments.</p>
    <section title="textBounds" level="3">
      <p><code>{x, y, width, height}</code> Specifies the bounds for the text inside the text box.</p>
    </section>
    <section title="textBackground / textBackgroundExtra" level="3">
      <p><code>textBackground</code> determines what image to use for the background of the text box. <code>textBackgroundExtra</code> is a table of extra overrides for the text box background image. In the above example it's used to place the background image at a custom position.</p>
    </section>
    <section title="nameTextBounds / nameTextBackground / nameTextBackgroundExtra" level="3">
      <p>The same as the corresponding <code>textBackground</code> attributes, but for the name box instead.</p>
    </section>    
  </section>

  <section title="Text Styling" level="2">
    <p>The default text style can be changed through the <code>text.defaultStyle</code> preference. It's also possible to change the text style partway through a sentence. The <code>style</code> function alters the current text style until the end of the current script line.</p>
    <p>The list of text style attributes that can be changed:</p>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Name</th><th>Type/Values</th><th>Description</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>fontName</th><td>string</td><td>The filename (without the .ttf) of the font to use.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>fontStyle</th><td>"plain", "bold", "italic", "bolditalic"</td><td>Makes the text bold/italic.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>fontSize</th><td>number</td><td>Determines the text size.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>anchor</th><td>number</td><td>Controls text alignment, corresponds to numpad directions (4=left, 6=right, 7=top left).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>color</th><td>number</td><td>Text ARGB color packed into a single integer (red=0xFFFF0000, green=0xFF00FF00, blue=0xFF0000FF, etc).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>underline</th><td>boolean</td><td>Set to true to make the text underlined.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>outlineSize</th><td>number</td><td>Thickness of the text outline (stroke).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>outlineColor</th><td>number</td><td>Outline ARGB color packed into a single integer (white=0xFFFFFFFF, black=0xFF000000, etc).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>shadowColor</th><td>number</td><td>Shadow ARGB color packed into a single integer (50% black=0x80000000, etc).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>shadowDx</th><td>number</td><td>Shadow x-offset.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>shadowDy</th><td>number</td><td>Shadow y-offset.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    
    <sourcecode lang="lvn"><![CDATA[Example with [style{color=0xFFFF0000}]red text[style()] in it.]]></sourcecode>
    
  </section>

  <section title="Custom Fonts" level="2">
    <p>Fonts must be places in the <code>res/font</code> folder. The <code>text.defaultStyle</code> preference can be used to change the default font — use <code>Build.jar</code> to change its value.</p>
    <p>To use a custom font or text style for a specific character, create a TextStyle object and pass it to the <code>say</code> function. TextStyle objects can be created using the <code>createStyle</code> function in the text module. See script function reference for more information.</p>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Text Log" level="2">
    <p>A history of the text displayed in the text box is stored in something called the text log. The number of pages kept in history is controlled by the <code>vn.textLogPageLimit</code> preference. Call the <code>textLog</code> funtion to display the text log.</p>
  </section>

  <section title="Non-English Languages" level="2">
    <p>The default font doesn't support every language. If letters display as empty rectangles, try using a different font. If the text shows up as completely different characters, make sure you've saved your script using UTF-8 encoding.</p>
  </section>
  
</section>
